*********SUMMARY: METHODS FOR ENDOSOMAL pH MODEL*********

The model is adapted from the lysosomal pH regulation model developed by Ishida et al. (2013). It is modified to describe endosomal pH regulation by incorporating the Na+/H+ exchanger NHE9, whose behaviour is adapted from Marcoline et al. (2016).

The system is formulated as a set of differential equations describing the entry and exit rates of different ions into and out of the endosome. The model consists of four main modules:

1. V-ATPase proton pumps
2. CLC-7 chloride/proton antiporters
3. Na+/H+ exchangers (NHE9)
4. Passive ion leaks

The concentration of each ion is regulated by contributions from the relevant transport processes. For example, H+ enters through V-ATPase and leaves through CLC-7, NHE9, and passive leakage.

***MEMBRANE POTENTIAL***
The membrane potential is calculated using a physical model established by Ryback et al. (1997), as also used by Ishida et al. The membrane potential depends on a number of parameters namely: The net charge accumulated inside the endosome, the membrane capacitance, Faraday's constant, endosomal surface area, volume, and the concentrations of permeant ions.
Impermeant negatively charged ions/proteins inside the endosome are represented by Donnan particles (B), which influence the distribution of permeant ions.
A positive membrane potential corresponds to an excess of positive charge inside the endosome relative to the cytoplasm.

***V-ATPase PROTON PUMP***
The V-ATPase pumps H+ into the endosome. The proton flux of a single pump (JV) is based on calibration against experimental current-voltage data from Grabe and Oster (2001). The pumping rate depends on:
- Endosomal pH (pHe)
- Endosomal membrane potential
The total V-ATPase proton flux is obtained by multiplying the flux of one pump by the total number of V-ATPase pumps (NV) on the endosomal membrane.

***CLC-7 CHLORIDE/PROTON ANTIPORTER***
CLC-7 Antiporter puts 2 Cl- ions into the endosome while pushing 1 H+ ion out of the endosome. The activity of a single CLC-7 antiporter is based on an analytical expression calibrated against electrophysiological recordings. Its activity depends on:
- Difference between cytoplasmic and endosomal pH
- Difference between cytoplasmic and endosomal Cl- concentrations
- Membrane potential/driving force
Total Cl- influx and H+ efflux are calculated by multiplying the single-antiporter flux by the total number of antiporters (NCl) and applying the appropriate stoichiometric coefficients (2 Cl- : 1 H+).

***PASSIVE ION LEAKS***
Passive channels allow H+, K+, and Na+ ions to enter or leave the endosome according to their electrochemical gradients. The passive flux is represented using a permeability-based formulation that depends on:
- Ion charge
- Endosomal membrane surface area
- Membrane potential
- Ion concentration

***NA+/H+ EXCHANGER (NHE9)***
NHE9 is included because it is an isoform found on endosomal membranes and contributes to endosomal pH regulation. Its activity is strongly dependent on endosomal pH. When the endosome becomes acidic:
- NHE9 activity increases.
- Excess H+ is transported out of the endosome.
- The exchanger therefore acts to restore the basal endosomal pH.
At higher endosomal pH values (basic pH), the activity of NHE9 is assumed to decrease and eventually become inactive. The NHE9 model was modified from Marcoline et al. (2016). Instead of the original linear decrease in activity between pH 6.55 and 7.25, the model uses a sigmoidal response. A reference pH of 6.85 is used in the activity formulation so that the decrease in NHE9 activity occurs across the approximately 6.55-7.25 range.The total NHE9 flux is calculated by multiplying the activity of a single exchanger by the total number of NHE9 exchangers. 

******OVERALL MODEL******
The complete model combines the independent transport modules into a coupled system of differential equations describing the dynamics of:
- H+
- Na+
- K+
- Cl-
- Membrane potential
- Endosomal pH

The final system captures the balance between proton pumping by V-ATPase, proton removal through CLC-7 and NHE9, passive ion leakage, ion exchange, and membrane-charge dynamics.

KEY REFERENCES

- Ishida et al. (2013): "A model of lysosomal pH regulation", DOI: 10.1085/jgp.201210930
- Ryback et al. (1997): "Theoretical considerations on the role of membrane potential in the regulation of endosomal pH." DOI: 10.1016/S0006-3495(97)78102-5
- Grabe and Oster (2001): "Regulation of Organelle Acidity" DOI: 10.1085/jgp.117.4.329
- Marcoline et al. (2016): "A mathematical model of osteoclast acidification during bone resorption" DOI: 10.1016/j.bone.2016.09.007